Guide to the Henry A. Ford Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
The Henry A. Ford Collection
January 1, 1832 - December 31, 1956
January 1, 1832 - December 31, 1919
Personal papers of Henry A. Ford a missionary during the mid-1800s.
5 linear feet
Ford, Henry A., 1819-1858
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
2011.013.0001
This collection is open to the public.
Henry A. Ford was born in 1819 in Lisle, New York, son of a Presbyterian minister. His father served a church in Broome County, New York. Dr. Ford was educated at Williams College in 1842 and then studied medicine at New York University until 1850.
In 1850 he married Olivia and entered service at the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions as missionary physician at Gabon, in West African country of Gabon from 1850-1854. He was accompanied by two other men, Best and Bushnell. When they arrived at Gabon they joined the Bushnell, Walker and Preston families. For the next four years Ford worked closely with the natives and learned a great deal about the region. Reverends Best and Wilson explored inland Africa during the years 1852-1853.
In 1855 Ford received the appointment of Commercial Agent from the United States, and resigned as a missionary. He returned to the United States and wrote African Fever Book. In 1856 Ford resigned his post as Commercial Agent and went back to Gabon to work as a missionary doctor. There he continued his missionary work until he died on February 3, 1858, in Gabon. Ford is the author of "Observations on the Fevers of the Western Coast of Africa".
Ford, Henry A., 1819-1858; Gabon; Seward, Frederick William, 1830-1915; Anderson, Rufus; Appleton, John; Ford, Olivia; Goodwin, Dolli; Walker, William; Wilson, John Leighton; Gabon--History--1839-1960; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. West Africa Mission; Medicine--History; Missionaries, Medical--Gabon--Biography; Slave trade--Africa, West
The Henry A. Ford Collection is part of a large number of collections and materials gathered by Charles M. Snyder, former History Professor at the State University College at Oswego. The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, printed materials, books, ledgers, and photographs dealing mostly with Henry A. Ford, his wife Olivia and their associates. The collection consists of correspondence and other papers relating chiefly to Henry A. Ford's missionary activities in Gabon including parts of a daily journal from 1854 to 1856, medical notes and family letters. Also included are missionary booklets, newspaper clippings and other miscellaneous materials. Mentions the slave trade in and around West Africa.
The collection has been divided into several series: correspondence, manuscripts, printed materials, ledgers, books, photographs, and miscellaneous. The manuscripts and correspondence have been divided into two sub-groups; original and copies. At present it is not known who copied either the correspondence or the manuscripts.
- Correspondence, 1832 - 1962 (Box-folder 01-01 to 01-27)
  Original correspondence precedes copied items. Both are arranged with incoming letters preceding the outgoing ones. Dr. Henry Ford’s letters are arranged first in chronological order, followed by his wife’s correspondence. The file B 11 has been kept together due to the subject. It contains all letters dealing with the subject of Dr. Ford’s appointment and resignation as Representative to the United States Government at Gabon, West Africa. It contains correspondence between Ford, Olivia and his colleagues and the government. File A 16 contains both original and copied material of Dr. Charles M. Snyder’s correspondence with the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. This file also contains a list of correspondence in the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions collections on Dr. Ford and his associates. Please see accompanying file Container_List_Henry_A_Ford_MS002.pdf for folder-level description.
- Manuscripts, 1834 - 1919 (Box-folder 01-28 to 03-07)
  Manuscripts are divided into original and copied. Dr. Ford’s journals are filed first. Due to the subject matter Dr. Ford’s personal notes on California and his medical notes have been kept together. Please see accompanying file Container_List_Henry_A_Ford_MS002.pdf for folder-level description.
- Printed Material, 1896 + n.d. (Box-folder 04-01 to 04-03)
  Printed materials have been filed according to subject or type. These are religion, school, maps and newspapers. Their connection with Dr. Ford is not yet known. The printed material is all original. Please see accompanying file Container_List_Henry_A_Ford_MS002.pdf for folder-level description.
  - Religion, n.d.
  - School, n.d.
  - Maps and Newspaper Articles
- Books, 1893 - 1897 (Box 04)
  The original owners of the books contained in the collection are unknown.
  - Webster, Daniel. The Bunker Hill Monument: Adams and Jefferson –Two Orations. [Boston, 1893]
  - Bendir, J.R. Die Hochzeitsriese. [Boston, 1897]
- Ledgers, n.d. (Box-folder 04-04)
  This series contains two book ledgers whose subject, origin, and dates are unknown. Their relationship to Dr. Ford is also unknown.
  - Unidentified Ledger, n.d.
  - Unidentified Ledger, n.d.
- Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 04-05 to 04-06)
  Two folders have been established containing those materials that are unidentified and unable to be filed within a particular series.
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 05)
  There are numerous photographs that are well preserved and in excellent condition. Unfortunately they are unidentified and undated.